Guide to the Art and Artifacts Records, 1915 - 2005 UA.01.07.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Art and Artifacts records
1915 - 2005
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. University Archives
UA.01.07.0001
2 Linear Feet
In January, 2005, funds granted by the Mary Duke Biddle Foundation allowed the Duke University Archives to survey University-owned paintings within the Perkins Library system. Prior to the survey, records of University-owned art that had been collected by University Archives staff, and these records were organized and collated with the new survey information. Collection includes lists, inventories, correspondence, clippings, notes, memoranda, photographs, and other materials generated 1915-2005 and related to art and artifacts owned by Duke University, including information on the portaits of the Trustees of The Duke Endowment painted by Douglas Chandor. Other artists represented include Charles S. Wiltschek, John Da Costa, Mary Lyde Hicks Williams, Norval H. Busey, Irene Price, Cedric Egeli, Simmie Knox, John A. Furlow, and Nelson Shanks. English.
1,300 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
No restrictions.
Provenance
The Art and Artifacts Records were compiled from a variety of sources by University Archives staff.
Historical Note
In January, 2005, funds granted by the Mary Duke Biddle Foundation allowed the Duke University Archives to survey University-owned paintings within the Perkins Library system. Prior to the survey, records of University-owned art that had been collected by University Archives staff, and these records were organized and collated with the new survey information. Over 100 works were identified, surveyed, and photographed. Approximately 80 other paintings were identified but not surveyed due to time constraints. A brochure was produced entitled Portraits in the Gothic Reading Room which detailed the history of the Gothic Reading Room of Perkins Library and the portraits it contains.
Collection Overview
Collection includes lists, inventories, correspondence, clippings, notes, memoranda, photographs, and other materials generated 1915-2005 and related to art and artifacts owned by Duke University, including information on the portraits of the Trustees of The Duke Endowment in the Gothic Reading Room painted by Douglas Chandor. Other artists represented include Charles S. Wiltschek, John Da Costa, Mary Lyde Hicks Williams, Norval H. Busey, Irene Price, Cedric Egeli, Simmie Knox, John A. Furlow, and Nelson Shanks.
Related Material
Frank C. Brown Papers, 1899-1943
Duke University Archives
Robert L. Flowers Records, 1891-1968
Duke University Archives
Malcolm Vaughn
Chandor's Portraits. New York: Brentano's, [1942]
Harold W. Lawrence
Douglas Chandor: An English Artist and his Texas Garden. Weatherford, TX: Antler Press, 1999
Chandor, Douglas, 1897-1953; Da Costa, John, 1867-1931; Duke Endowment; Duke University -- Art; Duke University -- History; Wiltschek, C. S.; Duke University. University Archives
- Subject Files, 1915-2005 and undated.
  Scope and Contents note
  Material mostly of unknown provenance, most of which appears to have been collected during previous attempts to survey and catalog University-owned artworks.
  - Lists of Artworks, 1915-2005 and undated (Box 1)
    Lists, inventories, memoranda, and letters describing University-owned artworks.
  - Gothic Reading Room, 1952-1997 and undated (Box 1)
    Lists of artworks and other information specific to the Gothic Reading Room of Perkins Library.
  - Gallery of Presidents Project, Gothic Reading Room, 1984-2005 and undated (Box 1)
    Correspondence, memoranda, invoices, and notes regarding the creation and installation of the Gallery of Presidents in the Gothic Reading Room.
  - Conservation of Portraits, 1965-2005 (Box 1)
    Correspondence, memoranda, invoices, and notes concerning conservation and restoration efforts for various University-owned artworks.
  - Nameplates, 1949-1991 (Box 1)
    Correspondence and notes regarding the ordering of nameplates for various University-owned artworks.
  - Art and History Preservation Committee, 1981-1982 and undated (Box 1)
    Correspondence, memoranda, notes, minutes, and other materials concerning the University Art and History Preservation Committee, which attempted a survey of university-owned artworks and an oral history program.
  - Artwork Loans to the Washington Duke Inn, 1988-2001 (Box 1)
    Correspondence, memoranda, notes, photographs, and other materials concerning University-owned artworks loaned to the Washington Duke Inn.
  - East Campus Artifacts, 1954-1983 and undated (Box 1)
    Brochures, notes, a list, and other materials concerning artworks on East Campus.
  - Faculty Commons: Inventory of Art and Artifacts, 1983-2000 and undated (Box 1)
    Memoranda, notes, and inventories concerning artworks in Faculty Commons.
  - Tower Historical Room, 1967 and undated (Box 1)
    Notes regarding the 1967 installation of a museum of Duke University history in the Tower Room of the Chapel.
  - Portrait Artists, 1985-1997 and undated (Box 1)
    Correspondence, memoranda, notes, promotional materials concerning portrait artists.
  - White House History: Journal of the White House Historical Association, 2005 (Box 1)
    Issue devoted to presidential portraiture. Includes information on artists Douglas Chandor, Simmie Knox, and Margaret Shoumatoff, all of whom have artwork at Duke.
- George G. Allen Ledger, 1927-1932 and undated.
  Ledger, letters, and receipts kept by George G. Allen, chair of the Board of Trustees of The Duke Endowment, concerning portraits of the members of the Endowment commissioned from Douglas Chandor. Correspondents include Douglas Chandor, Chandor's business manager Reeves Lewenthal, Duke University President William Preston Few, and Duke Endowment Trustees Norman A. Cocke, Charles I. Burkholder, Bennette E. Geer, and Robert L. Flowers.
  - Ledger, 1930-1932 (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1930-1931 (Box 1)
  - Portrait Receipts, 1930-1931 (Box 1)
  - Douglas Chandor Brochures, 1927 and undated (Box 1)
- Artworks Files.
  Records of individual artworks. Each work has its own folder containing survey forms, clippings, photographs, and other materials pertaining to that particular work of art.
  Arrangement note
  Files are divided into two subseries: works surveyed and works not surveyed.
  - Works Surveyed, 2005.
    - Portraits (Box 1)
      Arranged alphabetically by last name of subject.
    - Sill Life and Landscape Paintings (Box 1)
      Arranged alphabetically by last name of artist or by supplied title.
  - Works Not Surveyed, 2005.
    - Portraits (Box 1)
    - Sill Life and Landscape Paintings (Box 1)
- East Campus Survey, undated.
  - Photographs and file cards from a survey of artworks and artifacts on East Campus. (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Art and Artifacts Folders.
  - Desk: Captain Otway Burns (Box 2)
  - Desk: Cylinder Top (Box 2)
  - Desk: James Buchanan Duke (Box 2)
  - Desk: Stokes-Angier Library Secretary (Box 2)
  - Table: "Billy" Duke (Box 2)
  - Table: Roosevelt (Box 2)
  - Duke University Art Objects (Box 2)
  - Memorabilia: Artifacts, Objects, Relics, etc. (Box 2)
  - Duke University Plates (Box 2)
  - Tapestries (Box 2)
- Save Outdoor Sculpture, 1995-2001 and undated.
  - Notes, Clippings, and Correspondence, 1995-2001 and undated (Box 2)
  - Negatives, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Survey Forms, 1995 (Box 2)